Register of the V. V. Fedulenko Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
V. V. Fedulenko papers
1951-1975
2001C59
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet) >
Speeches and writings, and miscellany, relating to Russian participation in World War I, the Russian Civil War, and Russian émigré affairs.
Fedulenko, V. V. (Valentin V.)
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
V. V. Fedulenko was born in Kazan' on 22 February 1894. He graduated from the Alekseevskoe voennoe uchilishche in December 1914, was commissioned as an officer and sent to the front. Demobilized in January 1918, he returned to Kazan', where he joined the White Army in September of that year. He remained in its ranks until his evacuation from Vladivostok in October of 1922 with the flotilla of Admiral Iu. K. Stark.
His life and activities in Shanghai through the end of the Second World War were recorded in an oral history entitled Russian Émigré Life in Shanghai, by the University of California Berkeley Regional Oral History Office as part of its Russian émigrés project. At the conclusion of that war, Fedulenko was the deputy head of the Russian Emigrants Association of Shanghai, and assisted in the evacuation of thousands of Russians to Tubabao camp in the Philippines. Arriving in San Francisco in July 1950, he took an active role in helping the Russian refugees leave Tubabao for the United States and Australia.
In 1970, he published a history of the theater in Kazan' entitled Zarozhdenie i rastsvet teatra v Kazani. Fedulenko died in San Francisco in November 1974.
Chronology
1894 February 22 Born, Kazan', Russia
1970 Author, Zarozhdenie i rastsvet teatra v Kazani
1974 November Died, San Francisco, California
Scope and Content Note
Valentin Vasil'evich Fedulenko was a Russian army colonel who participated in the First World War and Russian Civil War in Siberia. The collection includes an oral history interview and writings of a historical and biographical nature.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Russia. Armiia--Officers; China.; Russia.; Russians--China.; Russians--United States.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; United States.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; World War, 1914-1918.
- Biographical File, 1951 and undated (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Letter of gratitude and military service record
- Speeches and Writings, 1960-1975 (Box 1)
  Articles, book, and oral history interview, arranged chronologically by title
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1951 and undated (Box 1)
  - Letter of gratitude (Folder 1: 1)
  - Military service record (Folder 1: 2)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1960-1975
  - "Posmertnye zapiski,", n.d. (Folder 1: 3)
    Typescript
  - "Uroki proshlogo," Russkaia zhizn', 1960 May 6 (Folder 1: 4)
  - "Kratkii ocherk o drevnikh slavianakh," Russkaia zhizn', 1961 July 1 (Folder 1: 5)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Rol' byvshikh soiuznikov Rossii po otnosheniiu k Belomu dvizheniiu," Russkaia zhizn',, and., 1961 November 24 and 30 December 7 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Russian Émigré Life in Shanghai, oral history interview, 1967 (Folder 1: 7)
    Printed copy
  - Zarozhdenie i rastsvet teatra v Kazani, 1970 (Folder 1: 8)
  - "Shestidesiatiletie Pervoi mirovoi voiny," Russkaia zhizn', [1974] (Folder 1: 9)
  - "Istoriia dal'nevostochnoi emigratsii," Russkaia zhizn', 1975 May (Folder 1: 10)